Guide to the G. Burton Wood Papers 1908-1987
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections and Archives Research Center
G. Burton Wood Papers
1908-1987
1946-1975
Wood, G. B. (Gregory Burton), 1909-
MSS Wood
2.70 cubic feet, including 6 photographs 4 boxes
Special Collections and Archives Research Center 121 The Valley Library Oregon State University Corvallis, OR, 97331-4501 Phone: 541-737-2075 Email: scarc@oregonstate.edu Web: http://scarc.library.oregonstate.edu/findingaids
The G. Burton Wood Papers document Wood's professional work as the Director of the Oregon State University Agricultural Experiment Station from 1966 to 1975 and as an agricultural economist. The collection includes trip and meeting files, speeches, and reference materials. Wood was a faculty member in agricultural economics at Oregon State University from 1951 until his retirement in 1975.
Biographical Note:
G. Burton Wood joined the faculty of Oregon State College in 1951 as head of the Department of Agricultural Economics, a position he held until 1966 when he was appointed Director of the Oregon State University Agricultural Experiment Station and Associate Dean of Agriculture. Wood retired from these positions in 1975. Wood earned a BS from the University of Oregon in 1938, an MS from Oregon State College, and a Ph.D. from the University of Wisconsin in 1945. From 1944 to 1951, he was on the faculty at Purdue University. Wood's specialities within agricultural economics were marketing, farm management, and arbitration.
Gregory Burton Wood was born in 1909 in Medford Oregon. He married Ramona Jackson, daughter of E.P. Jackson, in 1935 and they had two children, Gregory Jr. and Patricia. Wood died in 1990.
Henderson, Robert W. (Robert Wesley), 1914-2006.; Wood, G. B. (Gregory Burton), 1909-
Oregon State University. Agricultural Experiment Station; Oregon State University. Department of Agricultural and Resource Economics; Western Association of Agricultural Experiment Station Directors
Photographic prints.
Agricultural development projects--Turkey.; Agricultural economists--Oregon.; Agriculture--Economic aspects--Oregon.; Agriculture--Research--Oregon.; Crops--Research--Oregon.; Weeds--Control--Oregon.
Agriculture; Colleges and Universities; Economics and Banking; Oregon; Corvallis; Washington (State); Photographs
The materials were donated to the University Archives by Wood's daughter, Pat Gregory, in 1998.
Collection is open for research.
Oral history interviews of G. Burton Wood are available in the A.L. Strand Oral History Collection (OH 007) and the Horner Museum Oral History Collection (OH 010). Records documenting Wood’s administrative role and research are part of the Agricultural and Resource Economics Department Records (RG 128) and the Agricultural Experiment Station Records (RG 025). The Special Collections and Archives Research Center holds the papers of several other agricultural economics faculty including Emery N. Castle, D. Curtis Mumford, and Fred W. Obermiller as well as Elvin A. Duerst, Oregon State alumnus and international agricultural economist.
The G. Burton Wood Papers are arranged in 3 series: 1. Trip and Meeting Files, 1950 -1987; 2. Speeches and Presentations, 1946-1970; and 3. Reference Materials, 1908-1984.
The G. Burton Wood Papers document Wood's professional work as an agricultural economist and administrator. The collection consists of trip and meeting files, speeches, and reference materials The Papers reflect Wood’s representation of Oregon State University at special events, in meetings of Oregon commodity groups, and in regional associations and advisory groups. The bulk of the records are for Oregon, the Pacific Northwest, and the western United States. The collection also reflects Wood’s particular interests within agricultural economics – farm management, marketing, cooperative associations, the role of land grant colleges and universities, and the administration of agricultural research through Experiment Stations. Speeches, reports, and publications on agricultural forecasts and the future of agriculture broadly in Oregon and the Pacific Northwest are part of the collection. Also of note are materials pertaining to agriculture in Turkey assembled by Wood as part of a large Oregon State University contract with the United States Agency for International Development. Materials pertaining to mint oil, grape wine research, and the Winegrowers Council are part of the papers. Several photographs of groups of individuals (which may include Wood) are included as well.
- Trip and Meeting Files, 1950-1987; Series 1
  Series 1 comprises the bulk of the collection and documents conferences, meetings, and events that Wood attended in his role as an agricultural economist and Director of the Agricultural Experiment Station. As Director of the Agricultural Experiment Station, Wood represented Oregon State University at special events throughout the state of Oregon, in meetings of Oregon commodity groups, and in regional agricultural associations and advisory groups. The bulk of the records are for 1966-1975. This series includes materials assembled by Wood pertaining to agriculture in Turkey as part of an Oregon State University contract with the US Agency for International Development (USAID) to advise on the organization and coordination of agricultural research and extension programs and the development and prospects for agriculture in Turkey - especially production of wheat and other cereal grains.
  - USAID (United States Agency for International Development) Weed Control Project Meeting, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 1.01)
  - Agricultural Bankers Spring Conference Talk, 1972 (Box-folder 1.02)
  - Fall Agricultural Conference Meeting, 1974 (Box-folder 1.03)
  - Agricultural Research Foundation Investment Committee Meeting, 1987 (Box-folder 1.04)
  - Agricultural Research Institute (ARI) Governing Board, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 1.05)
  - Agricultural Research and Advisory Council Meeting, 1972 (Box-folder 1.06)
  - Albers Milling Co. Conference Meeting, 1974 (Box-folder 1.07)
  - American Arbitration Association, 1964-1972 (Box-folder 1.08)
  - American Bankers Association, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 1.09)
  - ASCS (Agricultural Stabilization and Conservation Service) Conference Trip Folder, 1975 (Box-folder 1.10)
  - Beef Cattle Day, 1972 (Box-folder 1.11)
  - Beef Cattle Field Day Meeting, 1973 (Box-folder 1.12)
  - Branch Station Superintendents Meeting, 1973 (Box-folder 1.13)
  - Community Banker Workshop, 1973 (Box-folder 1.14)
  - Crop Science Field Day, 1974 (Box-folder 1.15)
  - Department Heads Meeting, 1972 (Box-folder 1.16)
  - Interim Committee of ESCOP (Experiment Station Committee on Organization and Policy) Trip Folder, 1972 (Box-folder 1.17)
  - Annual Summer Meeting of Experiment Station Superintendents, 1974 (Box-folder 1.18)
  - Farm and Ranch Executive Seminar, 1974 (Box-folder 1.19)
  - Governmental Affairs Committee, Corvallis Chamber of Commerce, 1963-1965 (Box-folder 1.20)
  - Governmental Affairs Committee Chamber of Commerce, 1965-1966 (Box-folder 1.21)
  - Grape Wine Research Meeting, 1973 (Box-folder 1.22)
  - Annual Meeting of Gresham Cooperative, 1975 (Box-folder 1.23)
  - Jefferson County Livestock Association Meeting, 1973 (Box-folder 1.24)
  - Meeting with Mark T. Buchanan, 1973 (Box-folder 1.25)
  - Mint Oil Handling Evaluation and Recommendations, 1958-1962 (Box-folder 1.26)
  - Mint, Personal, 1958-1960 (Box-folder 1.27)
  - National Agricultural Outlook Conference, 1971 (Box-folder 1.28)
  - Twenty-First Annual Meeting of the National Research Council's Agricultural Research Institute, 1972 (Box-folder 1.29)
  - National Rural Development Conference, 1973 (Box-folder 1.30)
  - Northeast Regional Center for Cultural Development Trip Folder, 1972 (Box-folder 1.31)
  - Netarts Program and Graduate Student Budgets, 1973 (Box-folder 1.32)
  - Northwest Agricultural Show Talk, 1972 (Box-folder 1.33)
  - Northwest Food Processers Association Liaison Research Committee Meeting, 1972 (Box-folder 1.34)
  - Northwest Regional Meeting of Deans and Directors, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 1.35)
  - Meeting of the Nursery Industry, 1973 (Box-folder 1.36)
  - Oregon Agricultural Research and Advisory Council Meeting, 1974 (Box-folder 1.37)
  - Oregon Branch Experiment Station, Review Committee, Closure, 1972 (Box-folder 1.38)
  - Oregon Poultry Industries Association Meeting, 1973 (Box-folder 1.39)
  - Oregon Rural Areas Development Committee Meeting Talks, 1970 (Box-folder 1.40)
  - Oregon Turkey Improvement Association Meeting, 1972 (Box-folder 1.41)
  - Ornamentals Laboratory Dedication, 1974 (Box-folder 1.42)
  - OSU and USAID Contract for Weed Control Trip Folder, 1974 (Box-folder 1.43)
    USAID (United States Agency for International Development)
  - Pacific Northwest Agricultural Chemical Credit Conference Talk Trip, 1973 (Box-folder 1.44)
  - Pacific Northwest Conference on Agricultural Trade with Japan Meeting, 1974 (Box-folder 1.45)
  - Pacific Northwest Farm Forum Trip Folder, 1972 (Box-folder 1.46)
  - Annual PCA (Production Credit Association) Directors' and Managers' Meeting, 1974 (Box-folder 1.47)
  - Pear Bureau Meeting, 1972 (Box-folder 1.48)
  - Planning Session for Joint Meeting of WSRAC (Western Social Research Advisory Committee) and Extension Rural Development Group Trip Folder, 1972 (Box-folder 1.49)
  - Rangeland Resources Advisory Board Spring Meeting, 1974 (Box-folder 1.50)
  - Regional Bankers Agriculture Conference Meeting, 1973 (Box-folder 1.51)
  - Review of Agriculture Services to Outlying Islands Trip Folder, 1975 (Box-folder 1.52)
  - Scoggin Dam Meeting, 1973 (Box-folder 1.53)
  - Seattle Cedargreen, Personal Basic Data, 1950-1960 (Box-folder 1.54)
  - Seattle Cedargreen Report, 1960 (Box-folder 1.55)
  - Spring Agricultural Conference Trip Folder, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 1.56)
  - Squaw Butte Experiment Station Advisory Committee Meeting, 1972 (Box-folder 1.57)
  - Squaw Butte Beef Cattle Field Day, 1974 (Box-folder 1.58)
  - Superintendent's Annual Meeting, 1972 (Box-folder 1.59)
  - Southwest Washington Weed Association Meeting, 1973 (Box-folder 1.60)
  - Spring Agricultural Representative Conference, 1974 (Box-folder 1.61)
  - Tri-State Research Coordination Meeting, 1972 (Box-folder 1.62)
  - Turkey Agriculture Materials for Trip Folder, 1967-1973 (Box-folder 2.01)
    1 of 3 folders
  - Turkey Agriculture Materials for Trip Folder, 1967-1973 (Box-folder 2.02)
    2 of 3 folders
  - Turkey Agriculture Materials for Trip Folder, 1967-1973 (Box-folder 2.03)
    3 of 3 folders
  - U.S. Bank Agri-Business Talk Meeting, 1972-1975 (Box-folder 2.04)
  - U.S. National Bank Fall Agriculture Conference Meeting, 1973 (Box-folder 2.05)
  - Veterinary Medicine Isolation Facility Dedication, 1974 (Box-folder 2.06)
  - Western Farmers Association Meeting, 1974 (Box-folder 2.07)
  - Western Region Area Development Research Center Meeting, 1972 (Box-folder 2.08)
  - Western Regional Extension Committee Meeting, 1972 (Box-folder 2.09)
  - Western Regional Planning Meeting, 1973 (Box-folder 2.10)
  - W-113 Western Regional Technical Research Committee Meeting Trip Folder, 1973 (Box-folder 2.11)
  - W-113 Technical Committee, 1974 (Box-folder 2.12)
  - W-114 Annual Meeting Trip Folder, 1975 (Box-folder 2.13)
  - Winegrowers Council Meeting, 1974 (Box-folder 2.14)
  - Winegrowers Council of Oregon Meeting, 1974 (Box-folder 2.15)
  - WSRAC Meeting Trip Folder, 1973 (Box-folder 2.16)
    WSRAC (Western Social Research Advisory Committee)
  - WSRAC Meeting Trip Folder, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 2.17)
  - WSRAC Meeting Trip Folder, 1974 (Box-folder 2.18)
  - WSRAC Meeting, 1974 (Box-folder 2.19)
  - Yamhill Chamber of Commerce Harvest Dinner Meeting, 1974 (Box-folder 2.20)
  - Personal Notes on Others' Talks, 1965-1973 (Box-folder 2.21)
- Speeches and Presentations, 1946-1970; Series 2
  Series 2 consists of speeches and presentations given by Wood on a variety of topics at conferences and meetings; typed and reproduced speeches as well as handwritten outlines are included. Most of the speeches are from 1969-1970. Topics addressed include: markets for agricultural commodities, challenges of agricultural research especially in the context of Experiment Stations, the beef cattle industry in the Pacific Northwest, potato marketing and pricing, irrigation, the future of agriculture in Oregon and the Pacific Northwest; agricultural credit, and the commercialization of agriculture ("big agriculture").
  - Speeches Given, 1946-1970 (Box-folder 2.22)
- Reference Materials, 1908-1984; Series 3
  Series 3 consists of publications, reports, and reference materials received and assembled by Wood. They include publications by governmental and non-governmental organizations, Experiment Station materials, and newspaper clippings. The materials represent a wide range of topics including economic and agricultural forecasts, farmers cooperatives, the role of land grant colleges and universities, and agricultural research administration especially through Experiment Stations. This series also includes a 1908 postcard to Mrs. E.P. Jackson, Wood’s mother-in-law, as well as several photographs taken in the 1960s-1970s of groups that may include Wood. Materials pertaining to a committee studying the feasibility of a proposed OSU golf course are included. A directory from 1970 demonstrates Wood's professional contacts.
  - Agricultural Research Foundation Publications, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 2.23)
  - Curriculum, Ornamentals Short Course (Horticulture), 1959-1966 (Box-folder 2.24)
  - Department Reviews, 1968 (Box-folder 2.25)
  - Directories, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 2.26)
    Includes Deans of Agriculture, Experiment Station Directors, Other Departments, Branch Stations, Extension services, Oregon Agriculture Commodity and Farm Organization, Senate and House Comittees, ESCOP (Experiment Station Committee on Organization and Policy),WSRAC (Western Social Research Advisory Committee), WAERC - ERC (Western Agricultural Economics Research Council), USDA, and Northwest Soil and Water Conservation
  - Feasibility of a Proposed OSU Golf Course, 1978 (Box-folder 2.27)
  - Materials Relating to the Industrialization of Agriculture, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 2.28)
  - Materials Shared with Wood, 1961-1975 (Box-folder 2.29)
  - Materials Shared with Wood, 1967-1972 (Box-folder 2.30)
  - Newspaper Clippings- Farm Subsidies and Picking a University President, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 2.31)
  - Oregon Experiment Station Materials, 1973-1975 (Box-folder 2.32)
  - Oregon Commodity Data Sheets, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 2.33)
  - Others' Materials and Papers Presented, 1963-1972 (Box-folder 3.01)
  - Others' Materials and Papers Presented, 1966-1975 (Box-folder 3.02)
  - Papers by Others, 1961-1974 (Box-folder 3.03)
  - Photographs, circa 1965-1975 (Box-folder 3.04)
    Includes a photgraph of Roy Young with a field trip group (circa 1965) and 4 other photographs of unidentified groups (which may include Wood). Several of the photographs are by R. W. Henderson. One is a color print.
  - Photographic postcard to Mrs. E.P. Jackson, 1908 (Box-folder 3.05)
    Postcard from E.P. Jackson to Mrs. E.P. Jackson, parents of Wood's wife Ramona Wood (nee Jackson)
  - Publications and Materials by Government Agencies, 1960-1980 (Box-folder 3.06)
  - Publications and Materials by Government Agencies, 1962-1973 (Box-folder 3.07)
  - Publications and Materials by Government Agencies, 1967-1974 (Box-folder 4.01)
  - Publications and Materials by Non-Government Organizations, 1960-1976 (Box-folder 4.02)
  - Publications and Materials by Non-Government Organizations, 1965-1973 (Box-folder 4.03)
  - Quality and Food Task Force, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 4.04)
  - Report on Effects of Effluents on Flavor of Salmon Fish, 1966 (Box-folder 4.05)
  - Reprinted Publications, 1956-1968 (Box-folder 4.06)
  - A Review of the Pacific Northwest White Wheat Futures Contract, Report to the Governor, 1973 (Box-folder 4.07)
  - Western Agricultural Economics Association Publication, 1983 (Box-folder 4.08)